Welcome to Business Central Launch
Edition
a wave two 2026 and welcome to what's
new in finance and overview of all new
functionalities.
I will start first to explain what we
have here in this overview. We have some
improvements in excise taxes and self
billings. Both of these features were
delivered in a previous way, but we
listened your feedback and we improved
into this direction. Then we have a long
time waited functionality cross
environment master data management. I
will just show you an overview because
we have separate session for cross
environment master data management and
I'm encourage you to watch this session
to get all the details.
Then we enable withholding tax for
employees and I will just make an
overview
uh about localization updates we have in
this wave.
So, let's start first with excise taxes
improvements.
First feedback we received when we
delivered excise taxes were that in
previous version on the left side you
could add only one excise per item.
And it was a problem. For example,
if you have some um
drink sugar drinks or in in general you
have plastic and sugar in the same uh
item and you couldn't do it. So, we
decided to improve this feature. So, now
it's we do not have uh excise tax um
fast tab in the item card, but we have
uh new excise taxes page and you can
open this page from related on item
and you can add as many excise taxes you
have connected with this one item. 1 2 3
10 whatever you need. What is more
important, if you already started to use
excise taxes in the previous wave,
system will automatically upgrade
existing configuration to this new table
and new page. So, you don't need to
bother about that. It will be done
automatically.
What else we have about excise taxes?
This is something what is coming in
November minor, two new features.
>> [snorts]
>> Bonded location.
Uh
this is
uh let's say adding more complexity into
excise taxes. In simple models, it was
all good. But if you have bonded
location where you will not calculate
taxes in this situation, if this is
custom location location or whatever, so
now you can mark location uh not to
calculate excise duties
uh for inbound uh receipt of stock.
And the system will calculate excise
duty only when goods are released from
bond location.
So this is definitely new.
Uh again, it will it will be delivered
in November, but this is completely new
functionality. So if you have bonded
location, you can easily mark and you
can control what you want
um how you want to calculate when uh you
have in or out in the bond
uh locations. And based on that, you
have new
uh as a transfer entry type support in
excise permission because earlier you
had uh for sales purchase manufacturing,
but now we have transfer entry type as
well.
What else? Again,
we started with a um
specific calculation model in previous
uh release, and this is something what
is used in probably 90% of cases. So you
could calculate in the most of cases
excises, but again, we got the feedback
that in some rare situations, you
couldn't uh properly calculate because
we have sometimes ad valorem uh model.
And what does it mean? That this is not
calculated per volume or per quantity
per uh weight, but it is calculated per
uh amount.
So you need to calculate uh percent of
amount to get uh excise. This is mostly
related to taxations, but it can happen
in uh excise duties as well. So now you
will have new model ad valorem, where
you have formula here with excise will
be calculated using percent on a taxable
amount. So you'll be have taxable
amount, and system will use percent 10
or 20% you are applying to taxable
amount. And even more complicated
because in some, again, even more rare
situations, you have hybrid model. What
does it mean? That you have specific
component, for example, based on a
weight, and plus on the top of that ad
valorem component. So, now you will have
specific ad valorem and hybrid model
with combination of specific and well ad
valorem in excise calculations. So, this
is what is coming in November.
What else we have? As I mentioned in
introduction, we have self-billing
improvements. This improvement is
actually not so big on a first sight,
and it it came because your feedback was
that it can happen that you have
multiple vendors with self-billing, and
we had only one
number of series for self-billing
invoicing. So, now you have an option,
if you have multiple vendors for
self-billing, you can
select specific number series for each
of them, but if you do not have,
you if you do not select a specific
number series, system will take number
series you have on a payable purchase
and payable setup. So, this is up to
you. You can keep as is, and system will
just continue to use existing number of
series for all your vendors, or if you
have only one vendor, but if you have
multiple self-billing invoicing vendors,
you can select number series for all of
them, and system will work.
And one more thing on the top of that,
as because in the previous way we just
delivered this functionality, now in
this release, we will add PEPPOL format
on the top of that. So, self-billing
will be part of invoicing or e-documents
framework as well.
Now, as I said, only an overview, cross
environment master data management, I
will not go deep. As I said, we have
deep dive session about that, where you
will get all these details. Only what I
want to emphasize, we use the same
approach, the same user experience you
had earlier for master data management
in one one environment. So, you need to
go there.
So, now we already added additional
setup so you can use for cross
environment master data management. This
is definitely long time
uh required and missing functionality.
Especially when you have an example
multiple localizations, so you must have
multiple environment if you have
multiple localizations. So, now you can
enable cross environment master data
management easily if you have this
situation.
What else? Little bit about compliance
features.
Calculating withholding taxes for
employees.
In this example here on the screen, this
is apply for expense management and we
already have a session about withholding
taxes and expense agent, so you can go
there and get more details. But what I
wanted to emphasize here that
calculating withholding for employees is
not only expense agent functionality.
You can set up a withholding tax for
employees and to use for example in
general journal. So, you can use another
places as well. This is not only for
expense agent.
So, what we have there? We extended
existing withholding taxes
with vendors with a new option. So, when
you set up a business posting group, you
will have option to choose between
vendors and employees and system will be
behave based on that. When you choose
when you select employees as a business
posting group, then you will have
different calculations. You can choose
gross or net calculation, simple
calculation, different thresholds per
different periods and categories and
different models. So, this is much more
much bigger as a functionality than what
we already had for vendors. So, this is
not the last improvements in withholding
taxes. So, this is just next step
because we are planning to provide more
functionality in withholding tax as we
started vendors and now continue with
employees.
And the last
not the least important because this is
now about localizations. We have few
updates about localizations. So, I just
wanted to emphasize we will not talk
about them in details. What is important
very fact two enablement in Spain is now
in GA. So, you can use very fact two.
You need to set up. We have
documentation on our learn site. And if
you accidentally uninstall very fact two
feature, we have very fact two on
appsource as well. So, you can easily
install and set up for usage.
Because it will be mandatory from the
beginning of next year.
Now, we introduce invoicing for France.
It will be in GA as well. What else we
have? We expanded payment times for
Australia and Great Britain rules.
Then, we enabled new interstat reporting
in Germany based on new rules for
interstat core.
And we enabled fully structured address
for QR invoicing in Switzerland. So,
this is what is already inside. But in
November, December, we will deliver two
more features. One is really important
for Germany. This is about EU BP. So,
now you you will be able to export EU BP
files with audit file export only for
German localization. And we will enable
SFT in Austria and Iceland starting from
December. It will be standard
functionality we already have, but only
apply for Austria and Iceland
localizations.
So, this is maybe not everything what we
deliver in finance, but I tried to
emphasize about the most important
features in finance and the
localizations in this period.
So, thank you for watching this video.
>> [music]